Guide to the Cased Image File 1840-ongoing PR 12
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Daguerreotype, 2
  - Rosalie Schermerhorn [Gurney, Jeremiah], 1853/00/00 (Item 2-735)
    Young girl, seated on table next to chair, full length, left hand on top of chair, front view, hair parted in middle, curls, red dress with diagonal pattern, white socks, boots.
    Sitter is daughter of Mr. & Mrs. John P. Schermerhorn; similar to another portrait of Rosalie Schermerhorn in this collection.
  - Edmund Elmendorf (Item 2-736)
    Male figure, front view, half length, with white hair, wearing white foulard and dark jacket and vest.
  - Unidentified Young Female Halsey Family Member or Friend (Item 2-737)
    Seated female figure wearing fur stole and cuffs, black leather gloves, dark dress with white collar and brooch, positioned with right arm resting on adjacent table, hands on lap, facing 3/4 front view.
  - Mrs. Metcalf (Susan Whitlock) (Item 2-738)
    Female figure, 1/4 profile, wearing v-neck dress with lace up front, white blouse underneath, brooch, hair parted in middle, hands joined at lap.
  - John Drake Sloat (Item 2-739)
    Male figure in military uniform coat with bow tie, tassels, white shirt, clean shaven.
  - Tombstone of Hanny Read (?) (Item 2-740)
    Tombstone reads: "Hanny Read", trees and other tombstones in background, outdoors.
  - Henry Clay [Lawrence, Martin M.], 1845/00/00-ca1848/00/00 (Item 2-741)
    Portrait of a male figure (bust) wearing white collar, dark foulard, dimple in chin and hair over ears, key or brooch of some sort on lapel.
    Note identifies sitter and photographer.
  - Uzal Knapp [Esterly, D.] (Item 2-742)
    Male figure, front view, wearing eyeglasses on forehead, deeply wrinkled face, clean shaven.
    Accompanying notes describe history of sitter (entered American Army 1777, appointed Sergeant in Life Guards 1778, discharged by Washington 1783).
  - Jenet Gossman Dewitt (Item 2-743)
    3/4-length female figure, seated half-front, wearing all black except for white lace fringe in bonnet, wearing gloves.
  - 2 Unidentified Young Female Halsey Family Members or Friends (Item 2-744)
    Double portrait of young girls, taller girl is wearing white lace blouse and light colored skirt with knickers and tights showing, and holding umbrella in right hand; shorter girl is wearing large plaid blouse, high-water pants, boots, and is holding what
  - Unidentified Female Halsey Family Member or Friend [Beckers & Piard] (Item 2-745)
    Female figure wearing white bonnet, shawl, dark dress, hands folded on lap.
  - Unidentified Male Halsey Family Member or Friend (Item 2-746)
    Male figure, front view, wearing white shirt with high collar, dark jacket, black foulard, chain at neck.
  - Daniel Webster (Item 2-747)
    Male figure, front view, clean shaven, wearing high white collar, white shirt, black bow tie, dark coat, velvet collar, graying hair.
    Label adhered to velvet lining identifies sitter with coat of arms and "Vera Pro Gratis"; another label adhered to velvet states: "Presented to George Hall by Daniel Webster".
  - Clara Hood (post-mortem) (Item 2-749)
    1 year old girl, post-mortem, laying on back and covered with fringed paisley blanket, short sleeve dress with yellow sleeve bows, white socks, black shoes.
  - Unidentified Female DeGroot Family Member or Friend (Item 2-750)
    Female figure seated with her left arm resting on table, wearing gloves, dark coat with bracelet, brooch, cross hanging from neck, dark bonnet, white lace at base of bonnet/collar, holding an object in hands.
  - Unidentified Male Phelps Family or Salisbury Family Member [McCartey] (Item 2-751)
    Male figure, front view, hair parted on side, goatee, high white collar, black bow tie, white shirt, dark coat and vest.
  - Daniel F. Tiemann (Item 2-752)
    Male figure seated, half-length, bearded, gray hair, wearing high white collar, white shirt, black bow tie, black coat and vest, right elbow resting on table.
    Sitter was Mayor of New York City (1858-1860).
  - Mrs. Frances C. G. McWhorter and Alexander McWhorter (Item 2-753)
    Female figure and child, front view, female wearing white dress and child wearing red dress, background of green drapes, heavily hand-painted.
    Sitters are mother and son; may have been copied from an engraving by R. Paine.
  - Unidentified Infant [Cathan, L.], [1843-1850] (Item 2-753.1)
    Infant sleeping with head on white pillow, mouth open, eyes closed, feathered hat on chest, arm outstretched.
  - Ella Low, Harriet Low, Wm. G. Low Sr., A. Aug. Low, and S. Low (Item 2-754)
    5 children, 3/4 -length, L-R: young girl standing wearing off the shoulder dress with short sleeves, hair parted in middle, holding object in her right hand at waist level, left hand on shoulder of young boy to her left; young boy standing wearing check c
    Sitters are identified on accompanying paper, but writing is illegible.
  - Unidentified Landscape with Tollhouse [Cathan, L.], [1843-1850] (Item 2-755)
    Toll House sign on left with large building on right, street lamp, landscape with buildings in background, road in foreground.
  - Unidentified Landscape [Cathan, L.], [1843-1850] (Item 2-756)
    Buildings, Church spire, landscape.
  - Unidentified Landscape [Cathan, L.], [1843-1850] (Item 2-757)
    Landscape image with what appears to be a river, factories and one large tower in background.
  - Unidentified Harbor Landscape [Cathan, L.], [1843-1850] (Item 2-758)
    Harbor scene with ships and water in foreground and buildings in background.
  - George Hall [Root, S.; Root, M.A.], ca1850/00/00 (Item 2-759)
    Male figure, half front view, clean-shaven, wearing white shirt and black bow tie.
    Card catalogue states that sitter was President of the Village of Brooklyn, first mayor of the city of Brooklyn in 1834, 13th Mayor of City of Brooklyn 1855-1856.
  - Mrs. William Smith Valentine (Emily Bill) (Item 2-760)
    Female figure, front view, seated with head and paw of white dog on her lap, wearing dark bonnet with long sash under chin, black gloves.
    Accompanying note states that sitter is mother of Mrs. John Garthwaite Pierson (Marie Estelle Valentine) and grandmother of donor.
  - Unidentified Church (Item 2-761)
    View of side and front of white church with large white columns, trees, windows and bell tower.
  - Unidentified Landscape (Item 2-762)
    Landscape with farmhouses, trees and hills in background.
  - Unidentified Landscape (Item 2-763)
  - Unidentified Landscape (Item 2-764)
  - Great-grandmother Ward (Unidentified Female Ward Family Member) (Item 2-765)
    Female figure seated in high back chair draped with tasseled plaid shawl, sitter wearing light colored robe, white blouse, hair in curls, full view, hair parted in middle, looking off to her right.
  - Mary Ann Southweir or Unidentified Female Ward Family Member or Friend (Item 2-766)
    Bust of female figure wearing plaid bow tie, hair parted in middle, plaid/striped blouse, white collar, looking off to her lower right.
  - Grandfather Ward or Unidentified Young Male Ward Family Member or Friend (Item 2-767)
    Young male figure seated wearing black tie, white collar, plaid vest, dark jacket with black collar, right hand resting on arm of chair, chair facing 1/4 profile, sitter is smiling, hair parted on side.
  - Augustus Van Horne Ellis (Item 2-768)
    Male figure, 3/4-length, seated, front view, clean-shaven, wearing bow tie, white collar, coat buttoned up to neck with large buttons, arms folded in front of body, holding handkerchief?, brooch.
  - Unidentified Male and Female Webb Family Members or Friends (Item 2-769)
    Male and female figures seated, female wearing blue dress and black lace shawl with white collar and ties at neck, male with arm around back of female and legs crossed, wearing black jacket and bow tie, white shirt, black vest.
  - William Cullen Bryant (Item 2-772)
    Male figure seated front view with head turned 1/4 to his left, wearing plaid vest, black neckerchief, white collar and shirt, black coat, hands on lap, sideburns, gray hair.
  - John French Ellis, Samuel Carp Ellis, Elizabeth Van Horne and Gerard Stuyvesant [Brady, Mathew B., 1823-1896], [ca1843-1869] (Item 2-773)
    Four figures, L-R: Male figure seated with white beard and hair, arms crossed on chest, wearing black jacket, pants and vest, male figure standing wearing black coat and pants with polka dot tie and white collar, hair curly, clean shaven, his right hand r
  - Augustus Van Horne Ellis, Samuel Claudius Ellis, John Stoneacre Ellis, and Susan Margaret Ellis [Brady, Mathew B., 1823-1896], [ca1843-1869] (Item 2-774)
    Four figures, L-R: Young male seated wearing black jacket unbuttoned with vest, black neckerchief, white shirt and collar, white handkerchief in pocket, fringe on cuff, hair parted on side and long to ears; standing young male wearing black coat buttoned
    Sitters are daughter and sons of Samuel Carp Ellis.
  - John Knickerbocker Jr. and Elizabeth Winne Knickerbocker [Schapper, Garth] (Item 2-775)
    Male and female figures, seated, table with two books on it between them, female holding white material on her lap, male with legs crossed, wearing hat, and right hand resting on table; painting made in 1805/04/20
  - Matthew Galbraith Perry, 1852/00/00 (Item 2-776)
    Male figure, front view, clean-shaven, high white collar, black bow tie.
  - William H. Seward (Item 2-777)
    Male figure, front view, clean shaven, high white collar, black bow tie, thick eyebrows, grayish hair.
    Sitter was Governor of New York and a United States Senator, as well as the Secretary of State in Lincoln & Johnson Administrations who negotiated the purchase of Alaska from Russia.
  - Mrs. William H. Avirell (Mary Shute Williamson) [Stancliffe, J.W.] (Item 2-778)
    Female figure, front view, seated with right arm in back of chair and hand resting on top of chair, hair parted in middle, white collar and large dotted border bow tie, chain at waist.
    Sitter is daughter of Col. Robert P. Williamson.
  - Unidentified Male Beekman Family Member or Friend (Item 2-779)
    Male figure, full length, in clergy garb with white hair and left hand clutching rolled scroll on cloth-covered table
  - Mary Elizabeth De Peyster [Thompson, Josiah W.], 1849/00/00-ca1853/00/00 (Item 2-780)
    3/4-length portrait of seated female wearing white dress, earrings, brooch and lace collar.
    Card catalog states that sitter is the last surviving child of Frederick and Ann Beekman De Peyster, sister of Margaret James De Peyster.
  - Margaret James DePeyster [Thompson, Josiah W.], 1849/00/00-ca1853/00/00 (Item 2-781)
    3/4-length standing female figure, front view, wearing earrings and brooch and holding handkerchief.
    Card catalog states that sitter is daughter of Frederick and Ann Beekman De Peyster, sister of Mary Elizabeth De Peyster, and is unmarried.
  - Unidentified Male Honeywell Family Member (Item 2-782)
    Seated male figure, front view, face deeply wrinkled and aged, clean-shaven, high white collar black cravat, coat and vest.
  - George Hall, George H. Morris and John T. Morris, [ca1844-1885] (Item 2-783)
    Adult male figure with two young boys, front view, child to far left wearing 3/4 sleeve blouse, yellow buttons, child in middle wearing plaid dress, adult male is clean shaven wearing white shirt and hold child on right with both hands.
  - Unidentified Male and Female Jarvis Family Members or Friends (Item 2-784)
    Male and female figures, front view, female seated wearing black dress and gloves, white collar, hands on lap, brooch and monocle around neck, male standing in military uniform, insignia of the Army Engineers on his epaulets, white belt, gray hair.
  - Gerhard Caesar, Mrs. Gerhard Caesar (Catharina Angle Reiberg) and Johanna L. Traub (Item 2-786)
    Three figures, seated male figure on far left wearing black neckerchief and coat with white shirt and collar, gray hair, ring, his left hand in coat, female figure standing center wearing plaid dress with brooch, earrings, white blouse underneath, hair p
  - Matthew Galbraith Perry (Item 2-787)
    Male figure, 3/4-length, front view, dresses in uniform of Civil War period, left hand holding top of sword, right arm resting on table holding hat in hand, clean-shaven.
  - Mrs. John P. Schermerhorn (Louise P. Williamson) [Gurney, Jeremiah], [ca1839-1871] (Item 2-788)
    Female figure, head turned to left, hair parted in middle, white blouse with ribbon, piping.
    Original miniature painted in Paris by Dubourjal ca 1850.
  - Ephraim G. Squier or Unidentified Male Squier Family Member or Friend (Item 2-789)
    Male figure, seated, turned 3/4 to left, half length, bearded, wearing high white collar, black bow tie, right arm resting on table.
  - J. Schenk Suydam (Item 2-790)
    Male figure, half length, head turned slightly to right, bearded, sideburns, high white collar, black bow tie, white shirt, chain in vest.
    Accompanying newspaper clipping of sitter's obituary.
  - Unidentified Male (Item 2-791)
    Male figure, 1/4 profile, wearing black coat and vest, white neckerchief, hair short on top, long curls on sides, white.
  - Unidentified Female (Item 2-792)
    Female figure, front view, wearing floral patterned dress with dark shawl, large white bonnet with white ties in bow at neck, seated with her right hand resting on table, wearing black lace fingerless gloves, look to lower left of camera.
  - Unidentified Male (Item 2-793)
    Male figure, profile view, sideburns, beard, hair parted on side, wearing black jacket and bow-tie, white shirt and high white collar.
  - Mrs. W. G. Ward [Germon, Washington L.], ca1858/00/00 (Item 2-794)
    Female figure, standing with right arm on table, wearing earrings, white lace collar, white dress, belt at waist with chain and charm dangling from it, black lace shawl, freckled face.
  - Jenny Lind, 1850/10/00 (Item 2-794.1)
    Female figure seated beside table with scenic vase of flowers, black lace overdress, brooch, rings, right hand resting on table, belt around waist.
  - Julia Cheever (later Mrs. Alanson Warren) (Item 2-795)
    Full-length portrait of young girl standing with right hand on table, two books on table, wearing long curls, white dress, shoes and stockings.
  - House of John P. Schermerhorn, Morristown, N.J., with Unidentified Male, Unidentified Female and 2 Unidentified Young Females, 1855/10/10 (Item 2-796)
    Exterior view of white 2-story house with pitched roof, window on side of house, front porch with decorative pillars and borders, chimney on each side of roof, adult male and adult female figures on either side of 2 young girls standing on porch, trees in
  - John White (Item 2-797)
    Male figure right profile wearing polka dot neckerchief, curly hair, striped vest, dark jacket with black velvet collar, white shirt.
    Accompanying note states that sitter is brother of Mrs. John Steward.
  - Cornelia White or Unidentified Stuyvesant Family Member or Friend (Item 2-798)
    Female figure seated wearing lace collar, dark v-neck dress, lace cuffs, handkerchief on lap, hair parted in middle and pulled back, hands at lap, ring.
    White is sister of Mrs. John Steward
  - Mrs. John Steward (Catherine Elizabeth White) (Item 2-799)
    Female figure seated with one arm across waist, light dress with cape and fringes, white lace collar and cuffs, hair pulled back tightly and parted in middle, front view.
    Sitter is Mother of Mrs. Augustus Van Horne Stuyvesant St. (Harriet Leroy Steward).
  - Parke Godwin [Meade Brothers], 1850s (Item 2-800)
    Male figure, front view, wearing glasses, beard below chin, wearing striped vest, white shirt and collar, black jacket, standing, his right arm resting on chair back.
    Sitter is son-in-law of William Cullen Bryant; donor is grandson of sitter.
  - Mrs. Volney B. Palmer (Eliza Boyd) [Chase] (Item 2-801)
    Female figure, front view, seated with hair parted in middle, white lace blouse, pink bow tie, jacket laced half way up front.
  - Unidentified Young Female (Item 2-802)
    Young girl seated with right arm on table, trophy cup on table, wearing black off the shoulder dress, necklace, brooch, earrings, ring, hair in braided pigtails, parted in middle, 1/4 profile.
  - Asher B. Durand (Item 2-803)
    Male figure, front view, with both hands holding handle of cane or umbrella, wearing white shirt, bow tie, beard under chin.
    Sitter is an American artist and engraver.
  - 2 Unidentified Young Male Hurlbutt Family Members [Brady, Mathew B., 1823-1896], [ca1843-1869] (Item 2-804)
    Two young boys standing, taller boy has left arm around shorter boy, front view, both holding hats in hands, shorter boy is wearing large belt buckle and velvety coat with large bow tie, taller boy is wearing handkerchief in pocket, bow tie, chain on jack
  - Isaac Volney Baker, Laura D. Comstock Baker, Lucy Comstock Baker, Isaac V. Baker, Jr. and Charlie Kellogg Baker [Brady, Mathew B., 1823-1896], 1852/05/06 (Item 2-805)
    Group of five figures, L-R: Young boy seated on lap of female figure, boy is wearing paisley blouse with white pants and striped socks, fair-haired; Female figure seated with boy on lap is wearing black dress with white lace collar, brooch, striped bow at
  - Catherine Elizabeth Steward Stuyvesant and Anne White Stuyvesant (Item 2-806)
    Two young girls, one seated wearing yellow short-sleeved dress, bracelet, ring, hair pulled back tightly, one girl standing with left arm resting on shoulder of seated girl and right hand resting on right arm of seated girl, wearing dark dress with doily-
  - John White [Root, S.] (Item 2-807)
    Vignette of male figure wearing top hat, white background, sideburns, beard under chin, black jacket, white shirt, black foulard.
    Sitter is brother of Mrs. John Steward.
  - Mrs. W. G. Ward [Germon, Washington L.], ca1858/00/00 (Item 2-808)
    Female figure, seated, front view, wearing earrings, white lace collar, white dress, black shawl, chain on belt.
  - Mrs. C. A. Buckeley (Julia Neilson?) and children: John Buckeley, Charles Buckeley and Julia Buckeley (Item 2-809)
    Group portrait: Female adult seated, little girl on lap, young boys standing on either side of her, front view, full length, boy on right has his right hand on adult's shoulder, boy on left has one hand on adult's lap and one on his hip.
    Enclosed note identifies sitters.
  - Clarkson Crolius Jr., ca1855/00/00 (Item 2-810)
    Portrait (bust) of a male figure, front view, wearing white shirt and dark bow tie, sideburns, and collar up under chin.
  - Mrs. Edward Cooper and son Peter (Pierre) Cooper [Gurney, Jeremiah], [ca1839-1871] (Item 2-811)
    3/4-length double portrait of seated female figure with infant on lap; female wearing white collar, gloves, striped skirt; baby wearing white lace gown.
    Accompanying note describes sitters' histories: Cornelia Redmond was married in 1863 to Edward Cooper, and their son Peter, called Pierre, died during childhood.
  - James W. Cromwell, William Cromwell, Mrs. William Cromwell and 2 Unidentified Female Cromwell Family Members [Holmes, S. A. (Silas A.), 1819 or 20-1886], [1847-ca1858] (Item 2-812)
    5 Figures (four seated, one standing), L-R: seated female 1/4 profile, wearing white bonnet, white blouse, shawl, dark dress, hands on lap; standing young male wearing jacket with buttons down front, black bow tie at neck, white collar, dark pants; seated
  - Ella Low (Item 2-813)
    Young girl standing with left hand resting on back of chair, wearing black off the shoulder dress with locket on string around neck, hair pulled back, 3/4-length.
  - Mrs. Elizabeth Oakes Smith (Item 2-814)
    Female figure, front view, 3/4 length, seated, right arm resting on table, bracelets on both wrists, net on hair, earrings, white blouse, brooch, black dress.
    Note on case states that sitter is wife of Seba Smith.
  - Mrs. Matthew Galbraith Perry [Beckers, Alexander], 1858/00/00-ca1863/00/00 (Item 2-815)
    Female figure, seated, front view, 3/4-length, wearing black bonnet, white collar, holding white handkerchief in left hand, black dress.
  - Unidentified Young Male and Unidentified Young Female (Item 2-816)
    Young boy standing wearing high-water pants with scalloped cuffs, white tights, light colored off-the-shoulder blouse with buttons down front and scalloped lining, hair parted on side, his left arm around neck of young girl, right hand on arm of chair, yo
  - Unidentified Female and Unidentified Young Female [Langenheim, William, 1807-1874; Langenheim, Frederick, 1809-1879] (Item 2-817)
    Seated female figure, front view, wearing dark dress and black lace gloves, dark bonnet with black bow at neck, white collar, her left arm resting on back of seat, right hand holding left hand of young girl, girl wearing white bonnet, black dress (short s
  - Mr. and Mrs. Baxter (Item 2-818)
    Double portrait of male (seated at left), and female (standing at right) wearing fur hood
    Accompanying note is enclosed from Julia B. Livingston and identifies sitter's as her maternal grandparents.
  - Julia Dean [Gurney, Jeremiah], [ca1839-1871] (Item 2-819)
    3/4-length seated female figure leaning right elbow on table and wearing chain with cross, white collar, decorated ribbon in hair, rings, and dark dress with tasseled cuffs and velvet trim.
    Card catalog states that sitter was an American actress: "She appeared at the Bowery Theatre as Julia in 'The Hunchback'. She married Dr. Haybe in 1855 from whom she was later divorced."
  - John French Ellis, Dr. Samuel Carp Ellis, Elizabeth Ellis (Mrs. Robert B. Roosevelt) and Gerard Stuyvesant [Brady, Mathew B., 1823-1896], [ca1843-1869] (Item 2-820)
    Four figures, 3 male and one female (female and one male seated); front view, full length, seated male has white beard and hair, standing male on right holding cane.
    verso: "cu" in yellow paint; John French is father of Samuel Carp Ellis, who is husband of Elizabeth Van Horne Ellis; Accompanying note to Ellis Family Collection states family history.
  - Sue Ellis (Mrs. John Hewston Jr.) and 3 Young Male Ellis Family Members [Brady, Mathew B., 1823-1896], 1851/00/00-ca1852/00/00 (Item 2-821)
    Group portrait, 3 boys and 1 girls (2 boys seated); boys wearing rings, darks jackets, pants, white shirts, handkerchiefs, hair to below ears; girl wearing bracelet, plaid dress, white collar, curls.
    verso: "cu" painted yellow; Accompanying note to Ellis Family Collection states family history.
  - John T. Morris, Isabella T. Morris and William H. Morris (Item 2-822)
    Group portrait, three figures, two males seated, one female standing between, male on left is clean shaven with high white collar and black bow tie, holding book or Daguerreotype case on lap, female is wearing earrings, long yellow chain, left hand on rig
    John is uncle of George Hall Morris, Isabella is aunt of same, William is father of same.
  - Cornelia Brinkman Kip and Deborah Minturn Abbatt or Mary Abbatt (Item 2-823)
    Female figures seated with young girl standing adjacent, woman has her left elbow leaning on table, left hand holding left hand of girl, right hand around waist of girl, front view, full length, book on table.
    Accompanying note states that "Child is Cornelia Brinkham Kip who married William Henry Burr, a great uncle of the donor. She was the daughter of Henry Kip and his wife Elizabeth Minturn Abbatt. She is standing by one of her aunts, either Deborah Mintur
  - Morris Burr Ketchum (Item 2-824)
    Young male figure, 3/4 length, front view, seated with left arm resting on table, clean shaven, wearing white shirt and high white collar, black bow tie, right hand resting on right thigh, patterned vest, handkerchief in breast pocket.